Nikesh Shrestha, B.S.M.E.

sthan18@terpmail.umd.edu | 2617 Luiss Deane Drive, Parkville MD, 21234 | 410-419-2169

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/nikesh-shrestha-3518ba11b/ | Personal Website: https://nikeshshrestha2000.github.io/

Summary

Creative, inquisitive, and enthusiastic recent Mechanical Engineering graduate from the University of Maryland – College Park with multiple awards for academic excellence, and experience in product design, microdevices research, and design of electro-mechanical and autonomous systems. Possess strong technical communication, leadership, collaborative, and problem-solving ability.

Education

B.S. Mechanical Engineering

University of Maryland, College Park, MD

(Aug. 2018 – Dec. 2021)

Skills

- **Programming**: MATLAB, C++, Python, HTML5, Simulink, LabView
- Technical Skills: DMFA, Lean Manufacturing, Six Sigma, GD&T (ASME Y14.5), Human Factor Analysis
- Software: SolidWorks, Autodesk Inventor, Fusion 360, Ansys Workbench (FEA), Microsoft Office
- Machining: 3D Printing, Bandsaw, Lathe, Solder, CNC
- Languages: Fluent in English & Nepali, Conversant in French & Hindi

Work Experience

NJIT Advanced Energy Systems & Microdevices Laboratory

(Jun. 2021 – Aug. 2021)

Research Assistant (NSF REU Fellowship)

- Researched the implementation of surface tensions in a *microchannel* for *passive plasma separation*, and investigated the *visualization and characterization* of fluid drop on a surface treated PDMS material
- Successfully developed a MATLAB algorithm for autonomous detection and measurement of contact angles from images to increase research efficiency by reducing time and errors associated with manual measurement

Undergraduate Teaching Assistant

(Aug. 2020 – Dec. 2021)

- Courses: Electronics and Instrumentation II; Vibrations, Controls and Optimization I; Introductory C++ & MATLAB Programming
- Led 30+ student lab sessions by using *mentorship ability* and *presentation skills* to ensure understanding of course concepts and application to assignments/ lab reports

Technical Experience

Project: Redesigning Braking System for Triathlon Bikes

(Sep. 2021 – Dec. 2021)

Team Leader and Team Scribe

- *Increased safety* of triathletes while braking in aero position by *designing a hydraulic braking system* inside aerobars and utilizing engineering principles: *Product and Process Design & Lean Manufacturing*
- Utilized MATLAB, SolidWorks, Stack-up, GD&T, additive and subtractive manufacturing machines for design, analysis, simulation, and assembly
- Supervised project timeline and ensured quality of product to maximize customer satisfaction

Project: Autonomous Robot

(Jan. 2021 - May 2021)

- Fabricated a robot that autonomously detects and follows the operator at various speeds by programming *Arduino Uno microcontroller*, *PIR and Ultrasonic sensors*, and *actuators (DC and Servo Motors)*
- Networked data from Arduino IDE to Processing 3 for visual demonstration

Project: Time Series Analysis: Location Prediction of Dynamical System

(Sep. 2021 – Dec. 2021)

- Coded Supervised Probabilistic Model (Variational Sparse Gaussian Processes) using Python3 libraries (PyTorch, Scikit-learn, PyMC3) to forecast the 6D location and orientation of a Navy Battleship
- Achieved 91% testing accuracy average for 6-degrees within a 95% confidence bound with the model run time of less than 30 minutes for 20,000 data points

Project: Design and Model the Structure of a Helicopter

(Sep. 2019 – Dec. 2019)

CAD Designer and Team Scribe

- Successfully reconstructed all parts of a toy helicopter, including *complex shapes*, using *SolidWorks*
- Carried out Finite Element Analysis on critical internal and external parts to analyze structural integrity